The sky is inherently democratic.
السماء ديموقراطية بطبيعتها.
It's accessible, in principle, anyway, by anyone, everywhere,
فهي متاحة، نظريًا، بأي طريقة، ولأي شخص، ومن أي مكان،
just simply by the act of looking up.
فقط بالنظر لأعلى.
But like so many beautiful things around us,
ولكن مثل العديد من الأشياء الجميلة حولنا،
it's slipping away from us, and we haven't even noticed,
نفقدها باستمرار دون أن نلاحظ ذلك،
because we're honestly not really looking.
لأننا في الواقع لا ننظر إليها جيدًا.
So what do we look at instead?
فإلام ننظر إذن؟
Well, we look at our phones, we look at our computers,
حسنًا، ننظر إلى هواتفنا، وحواسيبنا،
we look at screens of all kinds.
والشاشات من كل نوع.
And honestly, we rarely even take the trouble
وحقيقة، نحن لا نكلف أنفسنا حتى
to look up enough to see each other,
بالنظر إلى بعضنا البعض،
let alone taking that next step to looking up at the actual sky.
فدعكم من النظر إلى السماء.
Now, there's a tendency to think that the loss of our dark night skies
الآن، هناك ميل للاعتقاد بأن فقدان سماء الليل المظلمة
is the inevitable outcome of progress, change, technology.
هو النتيجة الحتمية للتقدم، والتغيير، والتكنولوجيا.
And you know, that's just simply not true.
وذلك غير صحيح.
Later on, I'll tell you why.
وسأخبركم السبب لاحقًا.
But first, I want to tell you about my experience of the dark night sky.
ولكن أولاً، أود أن أخبركم عن تجربتي مع سماء الليل المظلمة.
I never saw a truly dark night sky until I was 15.
لم أشاهد سماءً مظلمة حقًا حتى بلغت 15 عامًا.
I was here, in Arizona.
وكنت هنا في (أريزونا).
I was on a road trip; I pulled over somewhere.
حيث كنت برحلة على الطريق ثم انعطفت بمكان ما،
I have no idea where I was, except I know what state.
ولم أكن أعلم شيئًا عن مكاني إلا اسم الولاية.
And I looked up,
ثم نظرت للأعلى،
and the sky was just filled with an impossible number of stars.
فكانت السماء مليئة بعدد لا يحصى من النجوم.
You see, I'm from New York City,
أنا من مدينة (نيويورك)،
and in New York, you can see the moon, you can see a couple of stars.
وفي (نيويورك) يمكنكم رؤية القمر، وعدد قليل من النجوم.
More often than not, they turn out to be airplanes when they land.
وغالبًا ما يتضح أنها طائرات عندما تهبط.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But there's really not much else.
ولا يوجد أكثر من ذلك.
As a result, most of my colleagues who are astronomers
ولذلك، فإن معظم زملائي من علماء الفلك
spent at least part of their youth looking up at the sky in their backyard.
أمضوا جزءًا من شبابهم وهم ينظرون إلى السماء في الفناء الخلفي،
I never really had that experience,
ولكني لم أحظ بتجربة مماثلة،
and, as a result, I'm really disappointing on camping trips.
ولذلك أكون مخيبة للآمال في رحلات التخييم.
I don't really know many constellations.
فأنا لا أعرف العديد من مجموعات النجوم.
The ones I do know, you probably know them, too.
وما أعرفه ربما تعرفونه أيضًا.
But I'll never forget that experience
ولكني لن أنسى أبدًا هذه التجربة،
of the first time I saw the dark night sky.
عندما رأيت السماء المظلمة للمرة الأولى.
And I was just flabbergasted at how many stars there were.
وذهلت لعدد النجوم الموجودة هناك.
And I felt tiny.
وشعرت بالضآلة.
Then I also felt like, "Where's this been hiding this whole time?
وتساءلت، "أين كان هذا مختبئًا طوال الوقت؟
Who's been hiding this sky from me?"
ومن أخفى هذه السماء عنى؟"
Of course, the answer is obvious if you think about it
وبالطبع فالإجابة واضحة إن فكرتم بها،
or if you look at the picture on the left,
أو إذا نظرتم إلى الصورة إلى اليسار،
where you're seeing the same neighborhood taken during a blackout
حيث ترون نفس الحي أثناء انقطاع الكهرباء
versus on an ordinary night.
في مقابل ليلة عادية.
You can't see the stars if you drown them out with light.
لا يمكنكم رؤية النجوم إن أغرقتموها بالضوء.
Take a look at our planet.
انظروا إلى كوكبنا.
This is our planet from space.
هذا هو كوكبنا من الفضاء.
Unlike stars, which are hot and glow invisible light so we can see them,
وبعكس النجوم الحارة التي تشع ضوءًا غير مرئي لنراها،
our planet is, astronomically speaking, pretty cold.
فكوكبنا بمعايير الفضاء بارد للغاية.
So it doesn't really glow.
فهو لا يشع بذاته.
When you see the planet looking like a blue-green marble
وعندما ترون الكوكب يشبه الرخام الأزرق والأخضر،
the way it does in this picture,
مثلما يبدو في هذه الصورة،
you're seeing it because the sunlight is reflecting off of it,
فذلك بسبب انعكاس أشعة الشمس فوق سطحه،
and that's why you can see the oceans, the clouds, the land.
وبذلك يمكننا رؤية المحيطات، والسحب، والأرض.
So if the sun wasn't shining on it,
لذا إن لم تشرق الشمس عليه،
we wouldn't be able to see the earth, right?
فلن نرى الأرض، أليس كذلك؟
Or would we?
أو ربما سنفعل؟
This is our earth at night,
هذه هي أرضنا في المساء،
and it is one of the most striking examples
وذلك واحد من أكثر الأمثلة إثارة
of how we have affected our planet on a global scale.
عن كيف أثرنا على كوكبنا على نطاق عالمي.
You can see light spidering out across the globe everywhere.
ويمكنكم رؤية الضوء ينساب من كل مكان في الأرض.
Now, of course, there are broad expanses of ocean that are still dark,
الآن بالطبع، هناك مساحات واسعة من المحيط لا تزال مظلمة،
and in many underdeveloped areas there's still darkness.
ومازالت العديد من المناطق المتخلفة مظلمة.
But you'll notice that this is a pretty global effect.
ولكنكم ستلاحظون أن التأثير عالمي.
We tend to think, when we think of places being lit up,
نحن نميل عندما نفكر في الأماكن المضيئة
of very extreme examples -- Times Square, the Vegas Strip.
إلى تذكر الأمثلة المتطرفة مثل (تايمز سكوير) و (فيجاس ستريب)
But really what that picture shows you
ولكن ما توضحه هذه الصورة
is that it's not just these extreme examples,
هو أنه ليس فقط هذه الأمثلة المتطرفة،
it's anywhere that uses outdoor lighting.
ولكن أي مكان يستخدم إنارة خارجية.
This tends to be a really dramatic effect on the ground.
ولذلك تأثير كبير على الأرض.
To understand why,
ولنفهم السبب،
all you really have to do is think about the shape of a lightbulb.
كل ما نحتاجه هو التفكير في شكل المصباح.
The lightbulb, for all practical purposes,
وشكل المصباح في كل الأغراض العملية
is more or less round.
يكون مستديرًا.
This is great for its original intended purpose of lighting up the indoors.
وذلك ملائم لغرضه الأصلي وهو الإنارة الداخلية.
You turn it on, light goes everywhere.
فبإضاءة المصباح ينتشر النور في كل مكان.
An individual light bulb can light up your whole room, more or less.
ومصباح واحد يكفي لإنارة غرفة كاملة.
Now, that's great if you're lighting the indoors,
وذلك ملائم في الإنارة الداخلية،
but in its application in outdoor lighting,
ولكن في الإنارة الخارجية
that traditional shape of the light bulb,
فهذا الشكل التقليدي للمصباح،
the sort of globe that spreads light everywhere,
الكرة التي تضيء في كل اتجاه،
is actually very inefficient.
يكون قليل الفعالية للغاية.
When you're outdoors, mostly what you care about
فما يعنينا بالخارج
is lighting the ground beneath you and your immediate surroundings.
هو إنارة الأرض تحتنا ومحيطنا المباشر.
All of that light that gets scattered outwards and upwards
وكل الضوء المتناثر للأعلى والخارج
doesn't actually help you light the area around you.
لا يساعد في إنارة محيطنا.
What it does is scatters up into the sky
وكل ما يفعله هو أنه ينتشر في السماء
and becomes what we call "light pollution."
ويصبح ما ندعوه "التلوث الضوئي".
Even if you don't care anything about stargazing, this should worry you,
حتى إن كنت لا تهتم بمشاهدة النجوم، ينبغي أن يقلقك ذلك،
because it means that 60-70% of the energy we use to light the outdoors
لأن ذلك يعني أن 60-70% من الطاقة التي نستخدمها للإنارة الخارجية
is wasted by blotting out the stars.
تُهدر في محو النجوم.
Now, like I said, I'm a big fan of technology.
كما ذكرت، أنا معجبة كبيرة بالتكنولوجيا.
Obviously, I use technology every day; I'm a scientist.
ومن الواضح أني أستخدمها كل يوم، فأنا عالمة.
And there's this tendency to say that it's progress that --
وهناك هذا الميل إلى القول بأن التقدم
you know, I'm not suggesting we're going to all go live by candlelight.
كما تعلمون، لن أقول أن نحيا جميعًا على ضوء الشموع.
Indeed, technology is allowing us to access the sky
بالفعل تتيح لنا التكنولوجيا سبر السماء
in ways that are impossible otherwise.
بشكل يبدو مستحيلًا بطرق أخرى.
One of the greatest examples of this is, of course, the Hubble Space Telescope.
وأحد أعظم الأمثلة على ذلك هو بالطبع تلسكوب (هابل) الفضائي.
The Hubble went up into space, it returns pictures daily,
فقد أُطلق (هابل) إلى الفضاء وهو يرسل الصور يوميًا،
and it allows us to see things
ويسمح لنا برؤية أشياء
that we are incapable of seeing with our naked eye,
لا نستطيع رؤيتها بعيوننا المجردة،
in ways that we've never been able to do before in all of human history.
وبطرق لم نكن قادرين عليها من قبل في التاريخ البشري.
Other examples of this would be planetarium shows.
من الأمثلة الأخرى على ذلك عروض القبة السماوية.
In the past couple of years, planetarium shows have become more high-tech
وفي السنوات القليلة الماضية، تطورت عروض القبة السماوية
with these great visualizations,
بوجود تصوير رائع.
and even though this isn't access directly to the sky,
وعلى الرغم من كون الاتصال بالسماء غير مباشر،
it's at least access to our knowledge about the sky.
فهو على الأقل اتصال بمعرفتنا عن السماء.
And indeed, we can experience the sky in a planetarium
وبالفعل يمكننا رؤية السماء في عرض القبة السماوية
in a way that is impossible for us to do
بطريقة يستحيل أن نفعلها
just sitting out and looking in the dark.
فقط بالجلوس خارجًا والنظر إلى الظلام.
All of you have heard of the Hubble Space Telescope and of planetariums.
جميعكم سمعتم عن تلسكوب (هابل) وعروض القبة السماوية.
But there are also ways for technology to enable participation
ولكن هناك طرق تكنولوجية لتمكين المشاركة
in people's experience of the sky
في رؤية الناس للسماء
that you may not be familiar with.
ربما لم تسمعوا بها.
These are called "citizen science projects."
وتدعى "مشروعات علوم المواطن".
Citizen science is when large research projects put their data online,
وعلوم المواطن هي عندما يتم وضع بيانات أبحاث ضخمة على الإنترنت،
teach ordinary people, like you, to go and interact with that data
ويتم تعليم أناس عاديين مثلكم ليتفاعلوا مع هذه البيانات
and actually contribute to the research
ويشاركوا بالفعل في الأبحاث
by making interesting or necessary characterizations about it.
عن طريق وضع توضيحات مهمة أو ضرورية عن الموضوع.
One such example of this is what I'm showing here, called "Galaxy Zoo."
وأحد الأمثلة على ذلك أقدمه هنا ويدعى "حديقة المجرات".
Galaxy Zoo is a project
وحديقة المجرات هو مشروع
where people get a 20-minute -- even less than that, actually -- tutorial
حيث يحصل الناس على برنامج تعليمي لمدة 20 دقيقة أو أقل من ذلك
on how to interact with these images of galaxies.
عن كيفية التفاعل مع صور المجرات.
They learn to annotate the images,
فيتعلمون التعليق على الصور،
and within a couple of minutes, they're up and running,
وفي خلال بضع دقائق، يكون بإمكانهم العمل،
and they're making really useful categorizations
ويقومون بتصنيفات هامة حقًا
and classifications of these galaxies.
وتبويبات لهذه المجرات.
Now, it's easy to understand
الآن، يمكن أن نفهم
why Galaxy Zoo would be an easy sell for people to be involved with:
لماذا يسهل الترويج لحديقة المجرات بين الناس:
it involves pretty pictures;
حيث يوجد صور جميلة،
galaxies are, generally speaking, pretty attractive.
فالمجرات بشكل عام تبدو جذابة للغاية.
However, there are many other flavors of citizen science projects
ومع ذلك، هناك العديد من النكهات الأخرى لمشاريع علوم المواطن
that people have delved into
التي يستكشفها الناس
that have varying levels of abstraction,
ولها مستويات مختلفة من التعقيد،
that you wouldn't necessarily think people would jump at.
لن تظنوا أن الناس قد يتطلعوا إليها.
One such example of this is the citizen science project
وأحد الأمثلة على ذلك هو مشروع علوم المواطن
associated with the mission that I'm part of,
المرتبط بالمهمة التي أعمل بها،
called the Kepler Mission.
وتسمى مهمة (كيبلر).
Kepler is a space telescope and it looks for planets around other stars
و (كيبلر) هو تلسكوب فضائي يبحث عن الكواكب حول النجوم الأخرى
by measuring the light from those stars very precisely.
عن طريق قياس الضوء القادم من هذه النجوم بدقة شديدة.
And we're looking for the dimmings
والبحث عن الخفوت
caused by stars blocking off some of that light.
الناتج عن حجب بعض هذا الضوء من النجوم.
We have an associated citizen science project called "Planet Hunters."
ولدينا مشروع علوم للمواطن مرتبط بذلك يدعى "صائدو الكواكب".
Planet Hunters gives you, like Galaxy Zoo, a short tutorial,
وصائدو الكواكب مثل حديقة المجرات يمنحكم تدريب مختصر،
and within a couple of minutes, you're up and running;
وفي خلال بضع دقائق يمكنكم العمل،
you're looking at data from the Kepler Mission
فتستعرضون بيانات من مهمة (كيبلر)
and looking for planets.
وتبحثون عن الكواكب.
The idea behind this is an easy sell, right?
وهذه الفكرة سهلة البيع، أليس كذلك؟
But the actual process of planet-hunting involves a lot of looking at graphs,
ولكن اصطياد الكواكب فعليًا يتضمن النظر كثيرًا إلى رسوم بيانية،
like the one I'm showing you here, and annotating them.
مثل المعروضة هنا، والتعليق عليها.
I do this all day and that doesn't even sound that interesting to me.
وأنا أفعل ذلك طوال اليوم ولا يبدو الأمر مثيرًا بالنسبة لي.
However, not only are people interested in doing this,
ومع ذلك، فالناس ليسوا مهتمين فقط بفعل ذلك،
but the citizen scientists that work with Planet Hunters
ولكن المواطنون العلماء الذين اشتركوا بصائدي الكواكب
have actually found planets in the data
قد عثروا بالفعل على كواكب في البيانات
that would have gone undiscovered otherwise.
والتي لم تكن لتكتشف بغير ذلك.
This is an author list from the paper that they published
هذه هي قائمة المؤلفين للبحث الذي نشروه
of the planet they discovered.
عن الكوكب الذي اكتشفوه.
You'll see that all the people who contributed are listed below,
سترون أنه قد تم ذكر جميع من ساهموا بالأسفل،
and it's sort of an odd amalgam of people's real names
وهو مزيج غريب من أسماء الناس الحقيقية
and their log-in names.
وأسماء تسجيل الدخول لهم.
You'll notice if you look carefully, this is the first academic acknowledgment
وستلاحظون إن نظرتم بإمعان، أن هذا هو أول اعتراف أكاديمي
of the importance of Irish coffee in the discovery process.
بأهمية القهوة الأيرلندية في عملية الاكتشاف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I don't want to give you the idea that these are some out-of-work scientists
لا أريد أن تظنوا أن هؤلاء هم بعض العلماء العاطلين عن العمل
or just a bunch of nerds that are really into this.
أو مجرد مجموعة من المهووسين بذلك الأمر.
There are 60,000 people who participate in these projects,
يوجد 60 ألف شخص يشتركون بهذه المشروعات،
and most of them don't have technical backgrounds.
وأغلبهم لا يملكون خلفية تقنية.
So clearly, what this is feeding into is people's curiosity
لذا من الواضح أن ذلك يغذي فضول الناس
and their willingness to be part of the scientific discovery process.
ورغبتهم في أن يصبحوا جزءًا من عملية الاكتشاف العلمي.
People want to do this.
الناس يرغبون في فعل ذلك.
But all of this technology
ولكن كل هذه التكنولوجيا
and all these digitally mediated ways of experiencing the sky
وكل هذه الوسائل الرقمية التي تساهم في التعرف على السماء
still have something of a feel to me like looking at an animal in a zoo.
مازالت تشبه مشاهدة الحيوانات بالحديقة.
It's a valid way of experiencing that thing --
فهي طريقة صالحة للتعرض لهذا الأمر...
indeed, the lion in the cage is still real,
فالأسد داخل القفص مازال حقيقيًا،
the Hubble images are indeed real,
وصور (هابل) مازالت حقيقية،
and you can get closer to a lion in a zoo than you can in the wild.
ويمكنك الاقتراب من الأسد في حديقة الحيوان أكثر مما تستطيع في البرية.
However, it's missing something.
غير أن الأمر يفتقد شيئًأ ما.
It's missing that savage beauty
يفتقد ذلك الجمال الوحشي
of experiencing that very thing in the wild for yourself,
لاختبار الأمر بذاتك في البرية،
unmediated by a screen.
دون توسط شاشة ما.
The experience of looking up
فاختبار النظر إلى الأعلى
and knowing that the sky you're looking at surrounds every known living thing
ومعرفة أن السماء التي تنظر إليها تحيط بكل شيء حي
in the universe
في الكون
is very profound.
بليغ للغاية.
Think about that for a moment.
فكروا بذلك لدقيقة.
We are the only planet we know of that has life on it.
نحن الكوكب الوحيد الذي نعرفه ويوجد عليه حياة.
The sky that you see is shared by every other living thing
والسماء التي نراها نشاركها مع كل الأحياء الأخرى
that we know of in existence.
التي نعرف بوجودها.
One of the things that I really like about my work
وأحد الأشياء التي احبها حقًا في عملي
is that it allows me to step back from my every day
هي أنه يسمح لي بالانسحاب من حياتي اليومية
and to experience the larger context,
والاندماج في كيان اكبر،
this feeling that just as we go out and try to find planets in the universe
هذا الشعور عندما نحاول العثور على كواكب أخرى في الكون
that might be like ours,
ربما تشبه كوكبنا،
it always reminds me of how precious what we have here is.
يذكرني بقيمة ما نملكه هنا.
Our night sky is like a natural resource,
فسماؤنا الليلية تشبه موردًا طبيعيًا،
it's as though it's a park that you can visit
كما لو أنها متنزه يمكنك زيارته
without ever having to travel there.
بدون الانتقال إليه.
But like any natural resource,
ولكن مثل أي مورد طبيعي،
if we don't protect it, if we don't preserve it and treasure it,
إذا لم نحميه ونحافظ عليه ونقدره،
it will slip away from us and be gone.
سوف يضيع من بين أيدينا.
So if you're interested in this,
لذا إن كنتم مهتمين بالأمر،
and this is something you want to learn more about,
ورغبتم في تعلم المزيد عنه،
I encourage you in particular to visit darksky.org
فيمكنكم زيارة موقع "darksky.org"
and to learn more about the choices you can make
لتتعرفوا على الخيارات المتاحة لكم
that can protect the dark night sky,
لحماية سماء الليل المظلمة،
because it belongs to everyone, it belongs to all of us,
لأنها تنتمي لكل شخص، هي تنتمي لنا جميعًا،
and therefore, it's ours to experience as we wish.
لذا هي لنا لنستمتع بها كما نشاء.
And it's also ours to lose.
وهي لنا أيضًا لنفقدها.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)